A Finding Aid to the Jack Stewart Papers, 1926-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.stewjack
Archives of American Art
Jack Stewart papers
1926-2010
AAA.stewjack
Archives of American Art
9.9 Linear feet
The Jack Stewart papers are dated 1926-2010 and measure 9.9 linear feet. A significant portion of the collection concerns Stewart's dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989), related research, writings, and exhibitions on the subject. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, printed material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials document his career as a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator.
Stewart, Jack
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2010 by Regina Stewart, widow of Jack Stewart.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. This collection is copyright restricted.
Biographical Note
Jack Stewart (1926-2005) was a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator in New York City. After developing an interest in graffiti in the 1970s, Stewart eventually wrote a dissertation on the subject, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989) and was recognized as an expert on mass transit art.
Jack Stewart began studying art at the High Museum School in his hometown of Atlanta when he was 10 years old. At age 14, he began a 4 year apprenticeship with painter and sculptor Steffen Thomas. After serving in World War II, he enrolled at Yale University (B.F.A. 1951) as a sculpture student, but soon switched to the painting department where he studied with Josef Albers and Willem de Kooning. After graduation, Stewart began receiving mural commissions and enrolled in classes at Columbia University School of Architecture (1951-1953). His interest in architecture was tied to understanding how to work effectively with architects on mural projects. Later, Stewart developed an interest in graffiti which he pursued through graduate study at New York University (M.A., 1975 and Ph.D., 1989).
Stewart created murals in ceramic tile, mixed media and stained glass. In addition to mosaic murals, he designed tables with mosaic tops. As an outgrowth of his mosaic work, Stewart developed a technique for laminating stained glass onto plate glass that, by eliminating the need for lead, opened new design possibilities. Mural commissions included work for Hamilton Hotel in Chicago, Versailles Hotel in Miami Beach, Public School 28 in New York City, and several ocean liners. The most unusual mural, Raw Material commissioned by Cluett Peabody and Company, was composed of shirt labels embedded in acrylic.
Beginning in 1950 Stewart participated regularly in group shows and enjoyed solo exhibitions mainly in the New York City area. He also showed in Philadelphia, Georgia, Rhode Island, Mexico and Italy, and was included in exhibitions circulated by the American Federation of Arts.
Stewart taught at the college level for nearly thirty years, including: The New School (art and architecture, 1953-1958); Pratt Institute (interior architectural design, 1955-1960); The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art (painting, drawing, human anatomy, art history, 1960-1976; Art Department Chairman, 1971-1976); International Center of Mythymna, American Division, Lesbos, Greece (summer school, 1962-1965); Columbia University (M.F.A. program instructor, 1966-1976); and New York University (drawing, 1967-1975). In 1976 he was appointed Vice President and Provost of the Rhode Island School of Design.
Stewart was active in several professional organizations. He served as New York Artists Equity Association Secretary (1986-1987) and President (1987-1989); President of the National Society of Mural Painters (1996-2000); member of the advisory board of the Steffen Thomas Museum and Archives, Buckhead, GA (1997- 2000s); and President of the Fine Arts Federation of New York (2003-2004). The National Academy of Design elected Jack Stewart an Academician in 1995.
Jack Stewart and Margot Schwarzhaupt, an artist, were married in 1947; they had one son, Brandon. Painter and arts administrator, Regina Serniak, became Jack Stewart's wife in 1976.
Jack Stewart died in New York City in 2005.
Scope and Content Note
The Jack Stewart papers are dated 1926-2010 and measure 9.9 linear feet. A significant portion of the collection concerns Stewart's dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989), related research, writings, and exhibitions on the subject. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, printed material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials document his career as a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator.
Biographical materials include a "Video Archive" (DVD) consisting mainly of Jack Stewart being interviewed on several occasions by Nancy Gold for her television show, "What It Takes." In addition to discussions about Stewart's career, the shows include examples of his paintings and murals along with views of him at work.
Correspondence mostly documents Stewart's artistic career and work as an educator and administrator; there is some personal correspondence, as well. Of particular note are letters to Rodman Townsend who commissioned a mural about the human brain; they discuss the details of the project and its evolution, brain research, and subsequent exhibitions of related paintings. Illustrated letters and greeting cards with original artwork are from Violet Baxter, Lorrie Goulet, Wolf Kahn, Clare Romano, Anthony Toney, and Sam Weiner. Herbert Brooks Walker sent several pieces of mail art and, while in Italy, collected graffiti information for Stewart. Letters Stewart wrote to his mother span decades; the best represented periods are the years he served in the U.S. Army and studied at Yale University.
Writings and notes consist of Stewart's dissertation ("Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway"), miscellaneous writings and notes, and art and architecture notebooks. Dissertation documentation includes the manuscript, drafts, and related records. Among the miscellaneous writings and notes - published and unpublished - are shorter pieces, articles, student papers, and teaching notes. Of particular interest are notes/instructions for a performance piece titled "Endless Subway," "Memories of Steffan Thomas" and "My Recollection of Charles Egan." Also found are minutes of Cooper Union adjunct faculty meetings (1965-1966), and reports written when provost of the Rhode Island School of Design. Art and architecture notebooks (5 volumes) were compiled while at Yale University.
Research files on graffiti contain many sound recordings and some transcripts of interviews with graffiti writers, voluminous lists of graffiti writers' names/tags, correspondence, notes, photographs, and a wide variety of printed material. Stewart began collecting these materials as his interest in graffiti developed. They were used for his dissertation and material continued to be added after the dissertation was completed.
Printed material mentioning Stewart or containing reproductions of his work includes exhibition catalogs, posters, and newsletters.
Artwork by Jack Stewart consists of drawings, paintings, and one etching; also found are designs and plans for tables, murals, and other projects. Drawings include figure studies, heads, and landscapes; most are in pencil and some in ink. The small number of paintings are oil on canvas (removed from stretchers), and gouache on paper and board. Sketchbooks (44 volumes) contain mostly pencil drawings and sketches, and a few studies for paintings and murals. Two volumes include writings about travels and events; of particular interest are "Notes on Kline's funeral May 1962," "Visit to Roman Bronze Art Foundry," and "Notes on My Development."
Photographic materials consist mainly photographs, but also include digital images and 35-mm color slides. Images of Stewart include views of him with paintings and working in his studio. Identified individuals with whom he appears are: Regina Stewart (wife), Brandon Stewart (son), Lil Stewart (mother), Ninalee Craig, Irving Sandler, and students in Urbino, Italy. Photographs of artwork document murals such as Raw Material (composed of shirt labels), and Versailles Hotel in Miami Beach; among the paintings documented are State of the Union, Icons of Western Art and Revelation XVI-16 (both with keys to individuals portrayed). Exhibition openings and installations are shown in photographs, color slides, and video recordings. Also found are photographs of the World Trade Center site taken by Stewart in December 2001.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1926-circa 2009 (Boxes 1,11; 0.6 linear foot)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1944-2009 (Boxes 1-2; 0.7 linear foot)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1947-2003 (Boxes 2-5; 3.1 linear foot)
Series 4: Research Files on Graffiti, 1972-2010 (Boxes 5-7,11; 2.8 linear foot)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1945-2002 (Boxes 8, 11, OV 13; 0.7 linear foot)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, circa 1990-2003 (Box 8; 0.2 linear foot)
Series 7: Artwork, 1946-2000 (Boxes 8, 11, OV 12; 0.3 linear foot)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, 1951-2004 (Boxes 8-9; 1.3 linear foot)
Series 9: Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-2010 (Boxes 10-11; 0.4 linear foot)
Baxter, Violet; Egan, Charles, 1911-; Gold, Nancy; Goulet, Lorrie, 1925-; Kahn, Wolf, 1927-; New York City Transit Authority; Romano, Clare; Thomas, Steffen, 1906-; Toney, Anthony; Townsend, Rodman; Walker, Herbert Brooks, 1927-; Weiner, Sam; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.); Yale University-Students; Art -- Study and teaching; Arts administrators--New York (State)--New York; Color slides; Designers--New York (State)--New York; Designs; Drawings; Graffiti; Graffiti artists; Greeting cards; Illustrated letters; Interviews; Mail art; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Painters -- New York (State)-- New York; Paintings; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Street art; Transcripts; Video recordings
- Biographical Materials, 1926-circa 2009; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1, 11
  Scope and Contents note
  Stewart's 75th birthday celebration at The Broom Street Gallery is recorded on a videocassette (VHS) and a DVD. Extensive information about family history, much of it compiled in the 1980s by Stewart's aunt and Travis Burns (nephew?) is included in "Lil: In Celebration of Lillie Ruth Hemperley Stewart's 99th Birthday, February 16, 2004" by Regina Stewart. Financial records consist of commissions and prices paid by decorators for mosaic murals, tables, and miscellaneous items. Legal documents include a birth certificate, U.S. Army honorable discharge papers; also found is certification of Stewart as an artist, allowing him to reside in his loft studio. The "Video Archive" recorded on DVD includes several television interviews with Stewart that include many views and discussion of his work.
  Arrangement note
  This series is alphabetized by folder title.
  - Addresses, Phone Numbers, Messages, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes and Resume, 1963-circa 2009; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "A Birthday Celebration for Jack Stewart, The Broome Street Gallery", 2001 January 30; 1 video cassette: VHS; 1 CD (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates, 1946-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Childhood Memorabilia (Box 1)
    - "Babyhood Days", 1926-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Binky Smith" Comic Strip, circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Elementary School Newspaper, Jack Stewart, Art Editor, circa 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - High School Notebooks, undated; 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - High School TrackTeam, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - High School Yearbook Advertisement, 1943; Oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - High School Yearbook, Alciphronian, Boys' High School, Atlanta, GA, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diplomas, 1931-1989; Oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family History, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial Records, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Identification and Membership Cards, undated; 1968-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Legal Documents, 1942-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Passports, Vaccination Certificates, International Driving Permits, 1962-1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 10th Annual Ocean Grove Memorial Day Art Event, 1991; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Video Archive, circa 2000s; 1 Videodiscs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Biographical Material from Box 1, Folder 6, 11, 13, circa 1938-1989 (Box 11)
- Correspondence, 1944-2009; Series 2; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence largely documents Stewart's professional activities; some purely personal letters are included, as well. Among the correspondents are galleries and museums, clients, publishers, universities, professional organizations, family, and friends. Correspondence post-dating Stewart's lifetime concerns donations of artwork and publication of his writings.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name or institution. Among the writings and notes (Series 3) is additional correspondence concerning Stewart's dissertation, and a book proposal for "Letters to Leaders from an Artist" (1992-1999) that may include copies of letters that do not appear also in this series. Also, a fair amount of correspondence is scattered throughout the research files on graffiti (Series 4).
  - AARP - Atlanta History Center, 1960-2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Baltimore Sun - Bush, George W., 1971-2003 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Candell, Victor - Columbia Museum of Art, 1967-2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Columbia University, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Committee to Support the President - Conte, Frank M., 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1961-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Corning Museum of Glass - Frankenthaler, Helen, 1961-1998; undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gallery and Studio - Gwinnett Council for the Arts, 1963-2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Heery and Heery Architects - Inoue, Izumi, undated; 1959-2006 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - International Institute of Language and the Arts, undated; 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jessica Dee Communications, Inc. - Lowrance, Mr. and Mrs. Richard, undated; 1959-2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Magnus, Dieter - Museum of the City of New York, undated; 1962-2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - National Academy of Design - National Endowment for the Arts, 1989-2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - National Society of Mural Painters - New York Transit Museum, 1961-2008 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New York University, undated; 1967-1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Nuell, Lon - Philadelphia Museum of Art, undated; 1957-2001 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Powers, Steve - Pyneburg, Henk, 1959-2008; undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Queens Museum - Sullivan, Rich, undated; 1959-2009 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Stewart, Mrs. Jack T. (mother), 1944-2002 (Box 1, Folder 39-42)
  - Stewart, Regina (wife) - Toney, Anthony, undated; 1975-2001 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Townsend, Rodman, 1984-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Travers, David B. V. - Vickrey, Bob and Marje, undated; 1946-2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Walker, Herbert Brooks, 1963-2002; undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Watson, Frank E. - Watson-Guptil Publications, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Weiner, Sam, 1984-2004; undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Weiss, Sonya - Zappala, Rosalie, 1946-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified, 1961-1999; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1947-2003; Series 3; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 2-5
  The dissertation manscript and various drafts are followed by related files, arranged alphabetically. Miscellaneous writings are arranged in rough chronological order. Additional writings are found in a few sketchbooks (Series 8).
  All writings are by Jack Stewart. There are drafts, related correspondence, notes and photocredits, as well as the completed manuscript of his dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978" (New York University, 1989). Miscellaneous writings and notes, published and unpublished, include shorter pieces, articles, student papers, and teaching notes. Of particular interest are notes/instructions for a performance piece titled "Endless Subway," "Memories of Steffan Thomas" and "My Recollections of Charles Egan." Also found are minutes of Cooper Union adjunct faculty meetings, and reports written when Stewart was Provost of the Rhode Island School of Design. Art and architectuure notebooks were compiled while Stewart was a student at Yale.
  - Dissertation, circa 1970s-circa 1989 (Box 2)
    - Manuscript, "An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978,", 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978," University Microfilms International, circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Drafts, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
    - Abstract, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Appendices, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, New York University and UMI Dissertation Abstracts, 1975-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Research, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Notes, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Photo Credits, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Proposal, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, 1960s-2003
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including Mass Transit Art Film Proposal, Artist's Statements and "Conceptual Development of My Art,", undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Writings and Notes about Indian Temples, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Certain Relationships between the Mosaics of Ravenna and Venice,", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Certain Symbolic Aspects of the Kailasantha Temple at Ellora, India, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Circumambulating the Kailasantha Temple at Ellora, India" and "The Importance of Glass through the Centuries,", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including "Endless Subway," Travel Diary and Trip Expenses, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Minutes of Cooper Union Adjunct Faculty Meetings, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Writings and Notes on Drawing, Color, and Travel Itinerary, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Student Notes, N.Y.U., 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Teaching Notes; Student Paper, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "The Paterson Lyric Opera Theatre: A History," Volumes 1-3, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - "Concepts of Intelligence: A Study of the Structure of Intellect Model," circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Notes on History of Mosaics; Student Paper, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Reports of Provost to Board of Trustees, Rhode Island School of Design, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Son of the Six Thousand Year Old Rakshasa,", circa 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Graphics Techniques: Intaglio;" Remarks on Colossal Sculpture, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including Articles on Films about Artists, Drawing, and "Mass Transit Art,", 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Writing and Notes including Proposal for "Murals in the Making," "Memories of Steffan Thomas," autobiographical notes, and sound cassette of "Arts Breaking," Feb. 4, 1993 WBAI Radio Program, 1990-1993; Includes 1 sound cassette (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Letters to Leaders from an Artist" (1992-1999), circa 1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Writings including Lecture Text, List of Paintings for 2000 Blue Hill Exhibition, and "My Recollection of Charles Egan,", 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Portfolio, "Selected Artworks of Jack Stewart, Ph.D., NA,", 2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art and Architecture Notebooks, circa 1947-1948
    - Art 10, (Prehistory - 16th century), circa 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Art 10, (16th century - 19th century), circa 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Architecture 10a (Overview; Egyptian - Moorish), circa 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Architecture 10b, part 1 (Fall of Rome - Gothic), circa 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Architecture 10b, part 2 (Renaissance - 20th century), circa 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Research Files on Graffiti, 1972-2010; Series 4; 2.8 Linear feet Boxes 5-7,11
  A high percentage of the items are dated circa 1975-1988, the years when Stewart was a graudate student at New York University. Items continued to be added after his dissertation was completed. Material added after 2004 largely concerns posthumously published writings. On occasion, these files have been referred to and possibly cited as Jack Stewart's "Mass Transit Art Graffiti collection."
  Published posthumously, Graffiti Kings: New York Mass Transit Art in the 1970s by Jack Stewart was based on his dissertation. Of particular note are the interviews, transcripts, lengthy lists of graffiti writers' names/"tags," and Profile of a Common Offender compiled by the New York City Police Department. Among the research files on graffiti is a copy of the first known instance of graffiti appearing in advertising - a Volvo ad showing the car parked in front of a graffiti covered wall.
  Some files are grouped by subject or record type. All are arranged alphabetically.
  - Advertisement, First Graffiti, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Auction, Guernsey's "Graffiti Art,", 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Book, Graffiti Kings: New York Mass Transit Art in the 1970s by Jack Stewart, 2008-2010; Includes 3 CDs (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Book, Mass Transit Art by Jack 7/Jack Stewart, undated; 1974-2004 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chronology, circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Clippings (1970s-2000s), undated (Box 5, Folder 10-17)
  - Coloring Book, 1977-1984 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - C-Prints List, undated; 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Exhibitions, Graffiti (Box 6)
    - The Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Christo del Bramante, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Fondation Cartier pour l'art contemporain, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Groninger Museum, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Various, undated, 1970s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Experience Music Project, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Films, Graffiti - Speedy by Julien Daniel, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Films about Graffiti - Kings of Broadway by Chris Pape, undated; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Films about Graffiti - Style Wars, circa 1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Fotofolio, Inc., 2001-2004 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Historical Background, Pre-historic-1970 (undated, 1940s-1980) (Box 6, Folder 13-15)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1973-1985; undated (Box 6, Folder 16-19)
  - Interviews with Graffiti Writers (Box 6)
    - "Graffiti Tapes", undated; 2 sound tape reels (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Meeting in studio with Tracy, Chi-Chi", undated; 1 Sound cassettes label reads "First side transfer from reel 2" (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - "Martinez Graffiti", 1973 December 20; 2 Sound cassettes 1 and 2 of 3; 3 not found (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "Lonie, T-168, Spring 1973", 1 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "Phase 2,T-168, Cat, use 1", 1974 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "Jack in studio with graffiti writers.", 1974; 1 Sound discs (CD) label reads "Cut from the film Wild Style, which follows" (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - "Lonnie", 1972; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Folder 24)